Now we come to the second aspect of managing projects, which is communication.
ننتقل الآن إلى الجانب الثاني من إدارة المشاريع، وهو التواصل.
Doing good work is, of course,
القيام بعمل جيد هو، بالطبع،
important, but not enough.
مهم، لكنه ليس كافياً.
Keeping the client in the loop of that good work is critical.
إبقاء العميل على اطلاع بهذا العمل الجيد أمر بالغ الأهمية.
It's also important to note here that most of
من المهم أيضًا ملاحظة أن معظم
the digital freelancing that you do could be done remotely.
العمل الرقمي الحر الذي تقوم به يمكن أن يتم عن بُعد.
You may never end up meeting the client in person.
قد لا ينتهي بك الأمر بمقابلة العميل شخصيًا.
This does leave room for misunderstandings and hence,
هذا يترك مجالًا لسوء الفهم وبالتالي،
the need to think about a communication strategy at the outset.
الحاجة إلى التفكير في استراتيجية اتصال في البداية.
Now, communication in the project could be of different types and at different levels.
الآن، يمكن أن يكون التواصل في المشروع من أنواع مختلفة وعلى مستويات مختلفة.
The most indispensable kind of communication is project status,
أكثر أنواع الاتصالات التي لا غنى عنها هي حالة المشروع،
which is nothing but informing what was done since the last update.
وهو لا شيء سوى الإعلام بما تم القيام به منذ التحديث الأخير.
This, as you can imagine,
هذا، كما تتخيل،
is the most common and obvious kind of communication in any project.
هو نوع الاتصال الأكثر شيوعًا ووضوحًا في أي مشروع.
The client wants to know where you are in the project and what's going to happen next.
يريد العميل معرفة مكانك في المشروع وماذا سيحدث بعد ذلك.
Now, this kind of communication is done through various means,
الآن، يتم هذا النوع من التواصل من خلال وسائل مختلفة،
depending on the size of the project and preference of the client.
حسب حجم المشروع وتفضيل العميل.
Some clients may want to use
قد يرغب بعض العملاء في استخدام
sophisticated project management tools like Trello or Wrike and others.
أدوات متطورة لإدارة المشاريع مثل Trello أو Wrike وغيرها.
Other clients may just be okay with e-mail updates coupled with calls with the client.
قد يفضل العملاء الآخرون تحديثات البريد الإلكتروني إلى جانب المكالمات مع العميل.
Other communication tools like
أدوات الاتصال الأخرى مثل
Slack and WhatsApp groups are also common for such updates.
مجموعات Slack وWhatsApp شائعة أيضًا لمثل هذه التحديثات.
It is also a good idea to maintain
إنها أيضًا فكرة جيدة للمحافظة على
a schedule to periodically update the client about the project's status.
جدول زمني لتحديث العميل بشكل دوري عن حالة المشروع.
This scheduling could also be facilitated by these tools.
يمكن أيضًا تسهيل هذا الجدول بواسطة هذه الأدوات.
You will see us coming back to project management tools later in the lesson and even
سترانا نعود إلى أدوات إدارة المشروع لاحقًا في الدرس
picking up one tool to see how we can use it to manage a client's project.
واختيار أداة واحدة لمعرفة كيف يمكننا استخدامها لإدارة مشروع العميل.
Now, another kind of update is conveying
الآن، هناك نوع آخر من التحديث ينقل
the design decisions of the solution that you make while you're working on the project.
قرارات التصميم للحل الذي تتخذه أثناء عملك في المشروع.
This kind of communication may or may not be asked for by the client,
قد يطلب العميل هذا النوع من الاتصال وقد لا يطلبه،
depending on the client's technical expertise in the project,
اعتمادًا على الخبرة الفنية للعميل في المشروع،
but it's important for you,
لكنه مهم بالنسبة لك،
as a freelancer,
وكموظف حر،
to convey these design decisions.
لنقل قرارات التصميم هذه.
This not only demonstrates your ability to think about
هذا لا يوضح فقط قدرتك على التفكير
a problem holistically instead of picking a one-sided approach,
في المشكلة بشكل كلي بدلاً من اختيار نهج أحادي الجانب،
but also demonstrates your expertise and knowledge in the task that you're working on.
ولكنه يوضح أيضًا خبرتك ومعرفتك بالمهمة التي تعمل عليها.
The client would really appreciate that you're
سيقدر العميل حقًا أنك
keeping them in the loop about how you're building the solution.
تبقيه على علم بكيفية بناء الحل.
This also educates them about the possible ways to work on the solution and
يؤدي هذا أيضًا إلى إخبارهم بالطرق الممكنة للعمل على الحل و
makes them gain confidence that they're investing in a well thought out solution.
يجعلهم يكتسبون الثقة بأنهم يستثمرون في حل مدروس جيدًا.
Lastly, this could be your chance to let them
أخيرًا، قد تكون هذه فرصتك للسماح لهم
know about the efficient means that you use to work on a solution,
بالتعرف على الوسائل الفعالة التي تستخدمها للعمل على حل،
making the work more productive and efficient.
لجعل العمل أكثر إنتاجية وكفاءة.
Now let's see what could be the examples of such kind of communication.
لننظر الآن فيما يمكن أن يكون أمثلة على هذا النوع من التواصل.
For example, if a client has asked you to make a script,
إذا طلب منك عميل أن تكتب نصًا مثلًا
to make all the numbers human-readable,
تجعل فيه كل الأرقام مقروءة للعين البشرية -
like adding commas, number formats,
مثل إضافة الفواصل وصيغ الأرقام
date and time formats,
وصيغ التاريخ والساعة
and so on in a web application,
وما إلى ذلك في تطبيق الويب،
you could just tell the client that you would do it through the Python humanize library.
فيمكنك أن تخبره أنك سوف تفعل ذلك من خلال مكتبة Python Humanize Library.
This will save a lot of time writing the code and hence would be more efficient.
سيوفر هذا الكثير من الوقت في كتابة التعليمات البرمجية وبالتالي سيكون أكثر كفاءة.
If you're working on a digital marketing solution and trying to find in-links,
إذا كنت تعمل على حل تسويقي رقمي وتحاول إيجاد الروابط الداخلية
you can inform the client of the design decision of not scraping the logs,
فيمكنك أن تخبر العميل بقرار التصميم بعدم تمشيط السجلات
but using a third party tool that can be used with commercial applications.
وإنما استخدام أداة طرف ثالث والتي يمكن استخدامها مع التطبيقات التجارية.
There could also be other kinds of design decisions,
من الممكن أن يكون هناك أنواع أخرى من قرارات التصميم أيضًا
like the design of the process itself.
كتصميم العملية نفسها.
For example, working on a detail spec before starting to build a module,
مثل العمل على خاصية تفصيلية قبل البدء في بناء نموذج
given the complexity of it.
على ضوء تعقيدها.